Hello. Good afternoon, everyone. Lower
this down just a little bit.
All right. Good afternoon, everybody. I
hope you had an excellent lunch. You're
feeling recharged and refreshed, ready
to start a double session here this
afternoon to learn about the Darwin Core
data package. I just need to close that
really quick. So hopefully you didn't
just stumble in here by accident.
Hopefully you here are here to to
actually join us today. If you did
stumble in, please stay. Uh what we are
going to do over the course of not just
this session but the next two sessions
today is bring forth an excellent group
of speakers to introduce the Darwin core
data package. This first session will
int will introduce the the the
generalities and the general concepts of
the data package through the through the
demon demonstrated through a series of
use cases. Our second session this
afternoon will then give you a little
bit more of the nuts and bolts and
nitty-gritty information that you would
be interested in. But before we start,
I'd like to take you take a few minutes
to help orient you uh with some helpful
information for today. And so the first
thing to know is what exactly is the
Darwin core data package? And I'm sure
there's a few of you in here who are
already aware of what it is. But for
those of you who are not, in a nutshell,
the Darwin core data package is a
publishing model that enables publishers
to share richer biodiversity data than
what is currently possible with the with
the Darwin core archives. So the Darwin
core data package mostly utilizes terms
from the from the Darwin Core standard,
but it also includes terms that are
governed by organi organizations outside
of TADWIG.
And I'm not going to linger overly long
on this slide here, but just to ease any
immediate concerns or anxiety um over
the potential of learning a new data
model and what that might look like,
let's just take a quick look at what
what the what the Darren, excuse me,
what the Darwin core data package is um
relative to the Darwin Core archives. So
what do they have in common? And so both
of these data models um have an
associated guide. They include a data
set metadata as in an EML.xml file and
our data shared as either a CSV or TSV.
But where biodiversity data shared in
the Darwin core archive format are
confined by cores and extensions and
limited by the star schema. The Darwin
core data package does not have those
limitations. Um, and that means that the
DAR core data package can support data
that are uh much more complex and that
cannot currently be supported, including
organism interactions, including um
identifications that support multiple
taxa and so forth. Now, let's have a
very quick look at our agenda for today.
And the first of our two sessions will
help you visualize the practical
implementation of the Darwin Core data
package uh with five use cases. And we
ask that you hold your questions until
the end of the session. So we we will go
through all of the use cases back to
back and then have time at the end to to
entertain any questions that you have
from there. At 3:30 we will have a 30
minute coffee break so everybody can go
out and stretch your legs, get some much
needed caffeine and then hopefully
you'll come back at 4:00 straight back
to this room. join us here to uh listen
to another five presentations addressing
many of the practicalities associated
with the data package. In the first
presentation then we'll provide a solid
there we go provide a solid overview of
how the data package came about um
drawing on the use cases presented here
in the first session. Um subsequent
presentations will provide um an
explanation uh of the relationship
between ABCD in the data package,
current imple implementation status of
the data package at GBF, an insight into
uh the data package publishing tools
that are currently in development or
being considered for development. And
then finally, you'll learn more about
how you can get involved in the current
public review process uh before we close
out the symposium for uh with a Q&A
session.
All right. So, there's some final
information that you definitely want to
know. Timing me. Oh, okay. Thanks. I'm
getting timed.
There's some information you're
definitely going to want to know as we
move into these upcoming presentations.
And this is going to be all about uh
what you're going to see in the
represent represented uh publishing
models used to implement the Darcore
data package. In this schematic, there
are six components. So the first
component are represented as events,
right? Events just as in Darwin core
archives are um or events are excuse me
things that happen at a particular place
in time.
Next you're going to see what are called
entities. So entities include
essentially interesting information
about an event or something that
happened.
The third component you'll see are
called agents. So agents are the things
that engage in an activity or an event.
An agent can be a person, a group of
people, or an organization, or even AI.
Next, we have join tables. And join
tables are exactly what they say they
are. They are tables that join
information about what happened to the
interesting things and the people or in
groups that did them.
Okay. So the with these publishing
schematics you will also see arrows and
so these arrows provide
directionalities. They link the tables
and show you how those tables are
linking to one another. And then finally
you're going to see what are called
predicates. And predicates are the words
or phrases associated with the arrows.
These are words or phrases that describe
the relationships between those tables
and relative to the directionality of
the arrows.
Hopefully that's clear. translucently
clear
maybe not crystal. Yeah. Excellent. All
right.
Perfect. Okay. So, bringing it all
together in a very simple example. I'm
probably running out of time, but we're
going to continue. Anyway, consider a
situation where you have an occurrence
with some additional information for
which there are no specific Darwin core
terms. In a Darwin core archive, you
would have an occurrence core table and
you would have an EMOF extension to
attach that extra information.
As a Darwin core data package, this same
information would be shared as follows.
You would have an inferred occurrence
that occurred during some event. Then
the additional information about that
occurrence would be connected to the
occurrence using an occurrence
assertion. So in this case, an assertion
in the Darwin core data package is the
equivalent uh is attaching the
equivalent information that you would
once use in uh in the EMOFH extension in
the Darwin core archives.
And without further ado, I would like to
say let's go ahead and get started with
sharing our presentations before anybody
thinks of any questions to interrupt.
And I would like to invite our first
speaker,
Karen Seltzer, who will be presenting.
Your your presentation's not up. You go
presenting on and a data use example
from my naturalist.
>> Thanks, Kate.
My name is Carrie Seltzer. I'm the head
of engagement for I Naturalist. And I'm
just going to stall for a moment while
my slides are pulled up, I hope. Um, and
great. So, I'm going to be uh showing
you how this Darwin Core data package
maps to I naturalist occurrence records.
I also want to give a huge thanks to
John who was tremendously helpful in um
helping me understand how I naturalist
data um maps to the data package.
Um so first of all if you're not
familiar with I naturalist um INAT
crowdsources observations and
identifications from all over the world
um and it's primarily photobased
um these
are occurrence records um and
occasionally there are also organism
interactions
associated with those occurrence
records.
Sharing biodiversity data is a huge part
of I naturalist mission. Um and so we
share a massive data set with GBIFF. Um
and I am pleased to highlight that uh if
you look at data since 2020 um more than
half of species have more than half of
their data from I naturalist. Um so
pleased to share how how this would
work. Just to recap for those of you who
maybe actually let me ask who who uses I
naturalist.
Okay, cool. Um, if you have not used D
naturalist, here's how it works. You see
something, you take a photo, like a
dragonfly for example, um, you
and at that point then people can either
confirm the identification if you've
submitted an identification of your own
or they can advance it or correct it if
you've made a mistake. Mistakes happen
all the time on our naturalist, but they
can always be corrected by the
community.
So, keep this flow in mind. a person
makes takes a photo of a thing, posts it
to I naturalist, and then other people
chime in and help with the
identification process because that's
we're going to come back to that and how
it maps to the data package. So, right
now we're sharing um we're sharing a
Darwin core archive with JBIFF. We
update it once a week hopefully. Um and
in terms of some of the limitations
right now uh we are not for example
passing along all of the identifiers
who've contributed to an occurrence
record. We're only passing along the
first one who uh the first person to
essentially like put that species level
identification.
Uh interactions are captured in I
naturalist um occasionally. It's not
part of our core data model. Um, but
this can be mapped to the Darwin core
archive format using the research,
sorry, resource relationship, but that's
not specific to interactions. Um, it
would sort of fit interactions into a a
more generalizable
uh structure there. And lastly, there's
a lot of additional data that we call
annotations in I naturalist. It's things
like life stage or plant phenology
stage. Um and right now a lot of those
are getting mapped to the dynamic
properties field. Um for example, leaf
phenology ends up there because there's
not a more structured way um to share
that in the Darwin core archive format.
So people are at the center of I
naturalist and so we're going to start
this mapping process with the agent
which if you have made an I naturalist
observation is you.
So you the event is you see something
that you want to take a picture of. So
now we've got you the event of you
seeing it and the thing that you saw.
You take a photo that is captured in the
media.
Then there's an identification and it
can come from you or it could come from
some someone else many other people.
And then there's that extra data like
life stage or plant phenology.
And with all of the records on I
naturalist as well as all of the media
there is a usage policy. We use the
creative common licenses. Um so that
fits in here too.
And we've got the provenence. Where did
these things come from?
So now when we start to pull into this
we see that there was an event conducted
by a person and in this case it was you
without there's not sampling effort um
it's just you saw a thing and you uh
took a photo. Um and that the
identification of what you saw is based
on the media. Um the identification was
is also mapped to an agent which like I
said can be you or someone else. Um and
the occurrence assertion is being made
about the occurrence which happened
during the event.
We're just going to keep adding more
arrows and boxes. So brace yourselves.
All right. So now we've got these join
tables in here. Those are the ones in
yellow. So now when it comes to media,
we've got media both about the the event
media about the occurrence, the
occurrence media about the occurrence.
We've got the media usage policy which
connects the media with the usage
policy. We've got proven provenence
media connecting those two boxes.
So this is sort of the core uh this is
how most of the I naturalist data that
we are currently sharing through the
Darwin core archive would get mapped to
the data package
and like I said we've also got these
interactions sometimes so now that comes
in and when we add the tables the
additional arrows and boxes to that
we've got media that is about this
organism interaction and the organism
interaction is happening with or by an
occurrence.
I know that's a lot to take in.
Uh if you want to see this sort of
captured in um in sort of a tabular
format, these are the key um the the key
tables that are included. There's some
links in the slides here if you'd like
to refer to the example data set that
John prepared. I forgot to mention that
from the outset that that was part of
this exercise was taking a very small
subset of I naturalist data that
happened to have that additional
information about uh in this case plant
animal interactions um that was used to
to to go through this exercise of
mapping I naturalist data to the data
package.
So when it comes to natural data using
this new format, there are many new
possibilities.
For example, one question that we get
fairly often is can projects be
represented in the data that is shared
with GBIFF. Um and this for example
could be part of providence. So I think
it opens up a new avenue for us to pass
on information that people have been
asking for uh in in in this u more
elaborate data model.
Another interesting possibility is that
the community ID which is essentially an
algorithmic thing on I naturalist it's
sort of a uh you the short hand is there
needs to be at least at least twothirds
agreement at the species level
identification for something to become
research grade and get shared with GBF.
And so that sort of simple algorithm
could for example be an agent in this
model if we wanted to sort of build out
the complexity of information that we're
passing from I naturalist um to a a a
data aggregator like GBF.
But when it comes to thinking about
where we are now using the Darwin core
archive to the implementation process,
we will need to think about a lot of uh
costs including complexity and
processing time and what are the
resulting file sizes and sharing this
way. It currently takes us about a week
to our Darwin core archive and we do it
once a week. So it's a constant process.
Um, if you've ever found it out of date,
it's because uh got too big and we
needed to optimize again.
So, with that, I am going to
say thank you and turn it over to the
next example.
Thank you Carrie for that awesome
example of citizen science data being
mapped to the DRO data package. Our next
speaker Yolichek will be providing an
example uh using natural history museum
collections. So probably something quite
familiar to everybody here.
>> Yeah. Hello, Daniel Kchek from Bhutanic
Museum in Berlin and I'm working at the
center for biodiversity informatics and
um collection data integration
um and I've been responsible for pushing
our data um for the last years to GIF
and likewise biodiversity networks. So
uh I knew a lot about um the limitations
of Darwin core and uh yeah so we were
happy to move one of the use cases to
publish natural history collection data
as D core packages.
So herarium we have in Berlin is um the
largest one in in in Germany. Uh right
now there's about 4 million specimens.
It has been largely destroyed during the
world war but it grew very fast again
due to the distribution of duplicates
and even now it's uh growing constantly
with about 30,000 new specimens per year
mainly through donations from botonists
or by collection uh events from our um
colleagues.
Um the type of data we provide or we are
able to provide are of course the
specimens currently about 4 million
ones. Um about 10% of them are digitized
so far as as high resolution images. U
they're stored as um diff data and we
provide them as JPEGs for the creation
of of thumbnails and of course um
through image viewers for humans to be
able to zoom into different um areas of
the image and to take measurements and
to rotate stuff like that.
We do have 30,000 images of um the
organisms before being collected. Um
often that's in the the original habitat
so that the surrounding um FL is also
captured and we do have um 30,000 tissue
samples and 50,000 DNA samples in our
DNA repository.
Um we do provide the sequences through
ENA and NCBI with nightly updates.
Um so far so before Darwin core data
package we provided only the specimen
and the specimen image to GIF um the
tissue and the material samples we
shared with the global genome
biodiversity network because um this
network also is able to um to show all
the associations between the objects. So
you can if you're looking for a DNA
sample, you can go to GGBN, it'll find
the DNA sample and then it will link you
to the um tissue sample this DNA has
been taken from and then to the specimen
that the tissue has been taken from and
as I said before the sequences are
shared with NCBI.
Um now again publishing model as Gary
showed. Um
again of course uh a specimen documents
the existing the existence of an
organism um the an event documents the
gathering event documents the existence
of an occurrence um at a given location
of course. And then all the materials
that get um that get um sampled or that
get gathered of course first is the
specimen that is the specimen gathered
on site. Uh later the material is taken
the material sample the tissue sample is
taken from the specimen
and the DNA is uh taken from from the
tissue sample. Um these are the the
arrows. They show that um this this this
chain of derivation and um the arrows
that I just added is um the only
exception. We have some tissue samples
that are not taken from specimen. For
example, if the tissues are taken
directly in the garden, there's no spec
specimen gathered. So the those tissue
samples are directly from the organism
in the garden.
Specimens is based of course on material
on the specimen with the exception then
if no specimen has been gathered then
the tification is of course based on the
organism in the mixture.
And we do have
of course um a lot of mu identifiers. So
these are glob unique and
identifiers for the specimens and the
tissue or the DNA samples they uh
resolve. So if you use them um
as as as a script you get the metadata
on on these objects as JSON. And if
you're a human using a browser then you
will get the same metadata as um a
landing page and of course the image
shown.
Um we provide certain geo assertions on
DNA samples for example and we of course
as mentioned we do have images of the
specimens as occurring media and of the
no of the specimens as material media
and of the occurrences. These are the
images of the living organisms.
Um the lessons we learned, we could
provide way more data that we could
before. And with this, there was also a
lot of more data issues to be
discovered. I learned a lot about um
control characters that can be that can
break uh a CSV and the IoT. um we found
almost every um special character or
control character in our data and we had
to clean them. Of course, we had to do a
lot of of juggling because the data
model of our database is very
normalized. So I had to concatenate a
lot of tables and um create a lot of
yeah SQL um statements for that and um
as I said as I showed in the example
there are a lot of objects that that
don't stick to the rules and um this was
just one example and uh we had to to
build a lot of workarounds for these
special cases that don't stick to the
regular um schema.
So together it was a lot of juggling but
in the end everything fit in and we were
able to write more more data than
before.
>> Yeah. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much. Sheriff I'd like to
invite our next speaker up, Ying Ming
Gan. She's going to give you an example
of the data package uh with complex
marine survey data and we are actually
quite a bit ahead of schedule.
Everybody's been super efficient in
their presentations. So, we'll keep
moving through our use cases, but this
will just give us a little bit more time
at the end for for discussion. So,
continue to hold on to your questions
and and comments and we will address
those at the end, but we'll just have a
little bit more time.
Oh,
thank you Kate. Thank you for inviting.
Thank you for being here. Good afternoon
everyone. I'm from Scott and
biodiversity portal which is also a dri
and obus node. So I'm very excited to
share with you how we use darling core
data package to map our complex marine
survey data sets.
The bird west fish data sets contains
fish records
for survey conducted from January to
March 2006
region in southern ocean. The goal is to
have a baseline assessment of the
biodiversity in that area.
It was published in year 2008
as a single parents table.
Now we remember how much more enrichment
of this data set can be done if we move
it to down core data package.
So first of all we have the events which
uh which consists of either the
rectangular midwater troll routine
sampling which is the first 200
target sampling which is
detecting the assemblage and lower the
to the depth of this assemblage and
sample the assemblage. So we have a
survey target that includes target taxum
life stage and body size for this
routine or target pull which happen
during an event.
And this sampling contains measurements
such as the depth mark over
size of the net as well as the trail
distance speeds and separate volume. And
this goes to the event assertion.
The fish sample will the occurrence and
we also indicate whether the occurrence
satisfied a survey target and all of the
fish were identified
and the identification goes to the
identification table.
Aside from the group of fish as an
occurrence, each of the individual fish
were also preserved as material
and their weight. So they contains the
dry and that weight as well as standard
length and energy content. This goes to
material assertion table. They are also
photographed. Each of the individual
fish were photographed. So we have the
of the material
and here to build on the tables the
materials goes here. Uh they they go
there are material atom event which
serves as an evidence for an occurrence
and that contains also the
identification as well as the material
assertion.
For some of the fish, their stomach
content was also assessed using
binocular. The prey item were identified
and counts and the degree of digestion
were recorded.
So to do this, the prayer items and its
identification goes to the material
table as a mixed material. Degree of
digestion is assertion to this material.
Now it is quite a complicated tables. In
total we have 23
tables which is all right. It cannot fit
into all the slides
and we were we had a thought exercise.
Can we map any with just D core archive?
So we could do most of the things with D
core archive. For example, the event can
still be an event core. Serve target and
survey will all generate from the humble
extension.
They got flattened into single table as
humble extension.
Occurrence material and notification and
media can go to the occurrence
extension. material assertion event
assertion can go to extended measurement
of fat extension that points to both
event or occurrence. Now this is where
we felt ding could data set well.
First of all there's less freedom in
specifying survey target. We want to
indicate a minimum body size um for for
the survey target and it's we can put
that as verbating target scope but it's
um more difficult to parse and then to
us we feel because the individual fish
has a material entity ID therefore
occurrence extension we make unique
occurrence ID to represent each row a
user occurs ID to represent material
feels a little awkward the
items were published because these the
media that is extension too far we can
use associated media but that will miss
the metadata such as the license of the
photo and the proactives we find that
it's difficult to represent in our
current extension
so these are the lessons that we learned
during the mapping. I thought we have to
join tables to get the foreign key just
to split them into multiple D core data
package tables and we find that tools
for splitting tables would be very
helpful.
Secondly, we think that it would be
extremely difficult to maintain the
identifiers upon updating the data set.
There are 23 tables and there are a lot
of identifiers to maintain.
Now within the dial data package is
extremely helpful to to model complex
data sets because it preserve the of the
data represented closer to the reality
and preserve the meaning of identifier
as well.
And finally I get go one step further to
see if we can access the data from D
core data package. A first use case we
could think of is the info detections.
This is ho extension intended to do
shell. So for example we have a target
scope of species ABC say we report
detections of an event of including all
the targets that we report that we
detected. So if we detect species C and
we report everything we can infer that
species A and B were not detected and
anything we detect outside of the target
scope are the non-target tax.
So using this concept I'm looking at
these four tables looking at what
occurrence
this data set
currents were reported. So looking at
the occurrence of all of the events that
are not that satisfy the server targets
um can be used to infer what they're not
present. So the yaxis are all the events
and x-axis are all the target scope. So
we can see the pale blue are the
detections from these detections only
data set.
A second use case what we thought of is
we be able to pull this data out for
data products. So in essential ocean
variables the fish line frequency
distribution is one of the sub
variables. So we want to see if we can
the fish length and build this fish uh
size frequency diagram.
So we look at the material assertion
where the fish lines are and then look
at how which
troll type it is from whether is from
routine or target troll that's uh that's
information in the survey table.
So the answer is yes we can do that we
can plot a fish line frequency
distribution.
So
during this process I also think you
know fish life frequency we we put it as
material assession but it could also be
an occurrence assertion. One of the
example from the OBC USA data set here
is um the you the diver could use this
tool here to measure the fish while
swimming and estimate the fish length.
So one thing is important is that when
aggregator will aggregate these data
sets the variables can come from
multiple classes. So push length can be
both occurrence assertion or material
assertion. We think this is important to
take into account so that user can pull
this data out.
And finally I personally like to see
what we can pull out the diet
composition from the ding core data
package. And yes it is possible we look
at the diet composition of pluragama
antarctic from birth routine uh from
sample from a routine to or the target
draw and these are what we found and all
this was not possible because the data
was unpublished.
So thank I would like to thank this list
of people who helped me so much in this
process and of course this data set was
a legacy data sets. There are mistakes
there are things that are incomplete
and um I do this as a data manager and
not not an ecologist. So um there will
be mistakes and finally um this mapping
is part of the contribution to the OBS
data coordination group. If you would
the coordinator group is open to
everyone. If you would like to involve
in this conversation with both J BF and
Obus please I would like to invite you
to join the coordination group and all
this is not possible without funings
from BPO and we are very grateful for
that and thank you so much.
Thank you very much for that, Ming. And
I'm trying to look out at the audience
and see how everybody's feeling. Kind of
gauging. Is everybody still feeling all
right? Not not feeling too queasy about
CH. Excellent. I see some thumbs up.
This is great to hear. So, three three
use cases in. We're getting a little bit
more complex. Maybe a lot more complex
with some of that marine data. We have
two more use cases to go. Both of these
are virtual presentations. So
presentation number four is is by Cecil
Cecilia Swenson and she is presenting a
use case that includes both citizen
science and DNA meta metabarcoding data.
>> Spinning and I will present how my
co-authors and I mapped a citizen
science and DNA meta barcoding survey to
Davinc code data package.
The data behind the diving court data
package mapping comes from a national
survey of flying insect diversity across
five different land covers. The project
was called insect mob.
Insect sampling was carried out by
volunteers that drove on pre-esigned 5
km routs with large nets mounted on the
rooftop of their car.
The end of the net could be detached
from the larger net after sampling and
the content shipped to the National
History Museum of Denmark for
identification.
The project consisted of a survey with
individual sampling events for which
there was collected material.
Some of the material was photographed
and identifications were based on both
morphology and DNA analysis.
We've previously shared the data as a
Davenco archive but some because of the
star schema limitation it was never
really a good fit and we wanted to see
if data could be better shared with
Davenco data package.
So if we go back to the Daven core
archive in the ideal world with the
table options we have in Darcore archive
we would first share the sampling events
and from those events we collected the
material.
We took images of that material. We
measured biomass of the bulk sample and
we extracted DNA. Occurrences was based
on both the DNA derived and the
morphological identifications.
However, this would not work in a
diamond core archive because we have
both extended information,
the event and the occurrence table.
And in a diamond core archive, you can
only have one core file, either an
event, occurrence or a taxon, and only
one layer of extensions to the core
file.
So the sampling event data had to be
shared as occurrence call in order to
include the DNA derived data extension.
This meant that media event information,
extended measurements of facts, and part
of the DNA derived information was
shared for each individual occurrence.
sample. An occurrence record of a growth
beetle in GIF includes an image of the
bulk sample the species was detected in
and not the individual itself.
And we had several images taken for each
bulk sample. So you can imagine how the
media quickly got inflated and did not
represent the organism that was detected
in the occurrence record.
So how would this data look like in
Davenport data package where we are not
restricted by the star schema?
I will now go through the tables we
included in the Davenport data package.
Some boxes or tables have dotted lines
around them. This means that they are
not actual tables included in the data
package but the information is included
in the tables they relate to.
Our citizen scientists were agents that
conducted surveys.
Each individual survey had a specific
land cover attack and tax target.
The agents followed a sampling protocol
to carry out the individual sampling
events.
During each sampling event, material was
collected. The material was bulk insect
samples and images were taken for some
of those samples.
The bulk insect samples were pro
processed into two size fractions and
dryweight biomass of the size sorted
material and DNA concentration of the
purified DNA extracts was captured as
material assertions
from the bulk sample. We performed
morphological identification of certain
texonom groups.
We then carried out nucleotide analysis
with three different primer pairs on a
fraction of the purified DNA extract by
following a molecular protocol.
And from one of those primer pairs, we
shared sequences sequences for which we
compared to a reference database to get
taxonomic identifications.
So we had identifications based on both
morphology and DNA sequences for which
occurrences could be inferred
which were then evidence of the
occurrence of taxa in an event and the
occurrences satisfied the survey targets
we set.
In total we map data to 12 tables in
Davenore data package.
We specified the preferred
identification, the DNA sequence with
the is accepted identification term.
We could elaborate on how material was
processed by including the part of and
derived from terms in the materials
table.
A quick reference guide and the
relationship explorer was a great help
to understand which tables would make
sense to prepare first in order to have
the identifiers needed to link between
the tables.
So, we went from a Diamond Core archive
with a core file of four extensions to
12 tables in the Diamond Core data
package.
If you're curious about which terms and
content we put into the individual
tables, you can find the use case
example in Sigma Beacon under the survey
folder in the Davenport data package
examples repo.
We found the Davenco data package
enabled us to establish the right links
between the data from the project and
share even more information that what
was previously been shared in a Davenco
archive. So Davinc code data package is
definitely a benefit fit for DNA meding
survey data.
Thank you all for your attention and I
hope you have an excellent time in
Bocota.
So, our final presenter, Holly Little,
was unable to join us here in person
today as planned due to the government
shutdown in the US, but she was able to
submit her presentation as a virtual
presentation, and I do believe she has
colleagues online to answer questions uh
when we get to the Q&A Q&A session at
the end. But I would like to now present
to you Holly Little's presentation. It's
present. She's presenting to you today a
use case on uh paleo data collections.
Just a moment.
Hi, I'm Paul informatics manager in the
department of biology at the Smithsonian
history with my co-authors. I'm here to
present a Darcore data package use case
for fossil specimens or as titled
characterizing paleontological specimens
for maximal alignment with global data
practices.
Informatics manager in the department of
paleobiology at the Smithsonian National
Museum of Natural History with my
co-authors. I'm here to present a
Darcore data package use case for fossil
specimens or as titled characterizing
paleontological specimens for maximal
alignment with global data practices.
Our use case addresses the mobilization
of data derived from specimens in
paleontological collections. These
collections cover evidence of all types
of life on Earth through time. And key
data points include documentation of
that material, the representation of
taxonomic occurrences through that
material, associated media, and
critically the geological context,
collections, event, and location
information for that material. Often
fossil specimens also include important
relationships, including biological
interactions and material associations.
Our overarching goal is to improve the
discoverability of paleo collections
data which is largely dependent on the
details listed here. Findability and
interoperability of key data points.
Ensuring there is clarity about what the
record represents in the physical
collection. Being able to share the
variety of associations or relationships
you might find with fossil specimens.
and having more options for fossil data
because of the variety and complexity of
data requirements.
For more context on the scope and
complexity, here's a brief, highly
selective and not comprehensive view of
that variety and fossils. As noted,
paleo collections cover the fossil
equivalent of all modern biodiversity
groups that includes plants,
invertebrates, vertebrates, trace
fossils, etc. A fossil specimen in a
collection could be a single microscopic
organism like this foram, a jar of them,
a single slide with thousands of fossil
pollen grains, a stratographic sample of
dozens of mollisks or a single mollisk,
a slab from the size of your hand to the
size of a treetop with many organisms on
it, a drill cord from across many
stratographic layers. and of course
large full skeletons that might be a
single organism or a composite of many.
Somewhat independent of the use case and
testing for the Daracore data package
development, we determined it was
necessary to try to categorize the wide
variety of fossil specimens to better
understand what the various types of
fossils we manage in the Paleo
collections are and to more clearly
define what the necessary data
structures are for each type. We worked
closely with the paleo community through
the paleo data working group to complete
this evaluation. Our working sheet is
shown in the screenshot here. This
effort resulted in three primary data
groups that inform the data structure
needed. Each data group covers many
different types of fossils as managed in
paleo collections. Group one standalone
record covers the most typical data
structure needed when a fossil specimen
can be represented by a single record
and most commonly a single taxon. Group
two relationships delves into
requirements for clearly defining
associations either biological or
material between individual taxonomic
occurrences contained within a single
object or sample of multiple objects.
Group three, complex strategraphy,
addresses fossil samples that may have
multiple geological context. This is
most often core samples.
That work has also helped us to develop
values that can be used to further
develop a vocabulary for a newer draw
core term, material entity type, which
is key for describing what a fossil
actually is.
Paleo collections have of course been
publishing data mapped to Darwin Core
using the Darwin Core archive model as
long as it has existed. But that version
does have limitations for meeting our
data publishing goals. Events and
localities are critical for paleo
research. While that data can be shared
with the Darwin core archive, it often
has limited discoverability.
Importantly,
in previous published data, it is
actually quite difficult to know what
exactly that record is documenting. For
example, if you're looking at a single
record for a fossil insect, you might
not know if that record represents
insects on a slab, as shown in the top
picture here, or insects in a piece of
amber, as shown in the bottom picture.
It also might not be clear that all of
these individual insects and one spider
of a variety of taxa are often found on
the same object in either case. In
addition, previous models have had
limited flexibility for using data
structures more tailored to the
different types of fossil specimens with
var variable specimen data.
Before divi so before divi div diving
into our mappings we wanted to share a
few caveats because the dial core data
package is much more dynamic. We
manually created our test data sets
record by record and term by term. We're
still refining those test test data sets
and piloting various iterations for each
data group. And it is quite possible we
will define more data groups as we go.
I'll also note that much of what we have
determined is likely adaptable for
modern or extent biological collections
as well since many of the data
requirements might be shared depending
on the type of collection.
So to start a major shift in the updates
to Dharma core and the Dharmaore data
package is use of material as the
primary class for collection specimen
data. This change introduces improved
options for clearly describing the
physical object represented by the
digital record
and an increased focus on events
improves discoverability of this class
of information and the connected
geological context terms. Expanded
tables for capturing agent data allows
us to share clear information about
people associated with our collections
or shared across collections which is
common for paleo. This part of the
mapping is pretty much shared across the
data groups. So for the rest of the
diagrams, we selectively remove some
tables for visual simplicity and clearer
focus on the more unique aspects of each
profile.
As we focus in on data group one and
some versions of data group 2 a, the
material relationship, we expand into
more tables. In our testing, we found a
few key areas that needed particular
attention and worked with the Dawn Core
data package team to address our
requirements. Location is not a real
class as it is embedded within event,
but we chose to show it in some form
here because of its importance to fossil
specimens. There can be a lot of nuance
in the relationships between collecting
events and locations with many to one
relationships in either direction. Due
to those nuances in the event and
location data, there can be some
variation in how to most clearly
describe the geological context. This is
addressed by having an ability to link
geological context to either event
directly to the material. In previous TY
meetings, you may have heard our group
talk about challenges with fossil
taxonomy. Having an ability to mobilize
the taxonomy used to build out the
published data set with a table like
identification taxon helps to address
any issues with aligning shared tax two
shared taxonomic backbones like the
catalog of life. And finally, we can now
use terms within the material table to
note those physical relationships to
other material entities.
As with other biological specimens,
fossil material entities have biological
relationships to other material
entities. For data group 2b, biological
relationships, we integrate the
occurrence table for improved mapping
and publishing of data about these types
of relationships. In fossils, this can
be found in many forms, including traces
like insect damage on a plant, a single
object that preserves encrusting of one
organism on another, as shown in two of
the images here, and an organism within
another organism, like these fish.
Referring back to the need for clarity
about what is physically present in the
collection, adding the material
relationship back into the biological
relationship model enables us to fully
describe many types of fossils. In the
images here, we see examples of fossil
insects, each included in our test data
as its own record. There are each
evidence of a taxa at a time and place,
so an occurrence. And they also all
happen to exist on the same piece of
shell. Therefore having a material
relationship and shared event location
and geological context data.
The model shifts to a much more event
centered version for group three. Here
we typically have a core or other type
of stratographic sample collected in one
event and at one locality which could
cross multiple stratographic layers and
therefore have multiple associated
geological context. That core might be
intact as a whole single object or it
may have been processed into multiple
subsamples as shown in the form slides
here which probably contain multiple
individual organisms each. In addition,
core samples include material beyond
biological. This mapping profile with
the Darwin core data package enables
publishing of a single data set to make
those events and associated material
discoverable even if only parts of that
data set are relevant to an aggregator
like GPIF.
In our work so far, we have developed
two test data sets using these three
mapping profiles. In total, the test
data sets use about 11 tables, but with
varying levels of emphasis and
complexity depending on the type of
fossil. Moving forward, we will
integrate additional tables that further
enhance these records as we continue
testing and evaluation. Given the range
of fossil types and challenges in the
data, this use of multiple mapping
profiles will be essential for fully
leveraging the Darwin core data package
for fossils from paleo collections.
Ultimately, the Darcore data package
does enable better representation of
that complexity than previous publishing
models.
While that is true, it will take work to
implement. As I noted in our caveats, we
had to map our data manually. Most
collections management systems do not
have the fields or tools to store or
generate some of the necessary data that
makes the DARO data package a powerful
publishing model. In particular, the
extensive and important use of
identifiers is something our community
doesn't quite have the ability to meet
yet. And as we all see with within our
communities, the resources and expertise
to adapt to a new system can vary widely
across collections and institutions.
To help meet the needs of the Paleo
collections community, we're working
with the Paleo data working group to
develop a library of shared resources
and tools in a new web resource we're
calling the Paleo data knowledge hub. We
are also working to create a Darwin core
implementation guide that is specific to
fossils from Paleo collections and will
address the Darwin data package once
finalized. We're also working to create
example records for the various fossil
types and data groups which can be used
to illustrate the full data mobilization
pipeline alongside the implementation
guide. And with that, thank you. We
really appreciate our partners in this
process, GBIFF and John, of course, and
a big shout out to the Paleo data
working group. Also, thanks to the
organizers for inviting us to contribute
to this session. We are more than happy
to talk about this use case in more
detail and any other details you might
be curious about for fossil data. Please
reach out with any questions, comments,
etc. My emails here and Erica and Alex
are available in the session for any
immediate questions you might have.
Thanks.
So this concludes uh the part of our
symposium where we present use cases and
I'm actually quite blown away not only
because all of the I I feel like all of
these presentations were absolutely
fantastic doing a great job hopefully
you think as well to explain what can be
quite difficult to to it to absorb as
far as thinking about your data in this
new data model context. The other thing
I find incredibly impressive is we are
15 minutes ahead of schedule and I can't
remember the last time I was at a
conference session where this happened.
So congratulations. This
thank you very much to all of our
speakers. This gives us another 15
minutes for Q&A. So it is currently
3:05. We have 25 minutes for questions
and I'd like to open the floor to to
anybody out there.
Uh well, thanks a lot for all the
presentation. I really enjoyed the use
cases. Um my question or my comment is
more about the usage of the data package
as a way to standardize the data. Um, I
work for a biodiversity observation
network in Quebec and Canada and we
uh are working to standardize the data
of a lot of researchers or sorry perhaps
I can move a bit uh researchers or our
partners have a lot of data and we often
encounter the same challenge is that
their data is very um unstructured.
They're basically uh uh Excel files and
they use some glosseries to like create
some unique identifiers and we found
that just standardizing
those data set into Darwin core uh
archives requires a lot of work and
often this is not budgeted or uh planned
and what I see with the data package is
that there is a great opportunity to
have more richness, but I have a concern
that it will require exponentially more
effort to standardize the data and we
still have the challenge of there's not
a lot of money or efforts put into that.
So, I'd love to hear uh your comments on
that effort to standardize and how we
can work toward this with this new
standard.
Hello. Um,
that might be a question better suited
for later, but we have so much time I'm
going to take it. And the answer is
complex.
We already have problems with resources
with mapping Darwin core archives.
The big message here is that Darwin core
data packages enable those who need to
do something more than they can do
already and have the resources to do it.
We all want to find resources to do
things more be more better and richer
um and to try to do if if those
researchers have more data than they can
mobilize via a Darwin core archive, they
have a choice. find those resources and
publish in a Darwin core archive or use
a sorry in a Darwin core data package or
do things the way things are now not
include all that richness and use Darwin
core archives both will continue to be
supportive
does that help
Thanks.
Um, so this is just to kind of check
where everybody is with this sort of
stuff. Uh, so the Darwin core data
package, I just checked the GitHub and
it's quite sprawling. um but luckily
very formally described apparently in
JSON. So I saw in some of the talks
people saying well this is really
complex to map onto this. I have a SQL
database with complex joins. I have the
my tables and I'm just curious to hear
would other people do the thing that I
would do which is to load the Darwin
core data package description into an
LLM and then have it talk me through
what I'm supposed to do or it be I mean
this is too big for our own brains it
feels like to me so I don't know if
anybody else is doing the same thing
here
not just me okay
cool thanks
Just one second. We have two questions
online. So, we'll take one of those.
>> So, one question is from Matias Dylan.
He's asking, "More tables mean more
identifiers. And what should they do
with the occurrence IDs they currently
have in Darcore archives? Do they want
to transform it to Darwin core data
packages? How many more identifiers do
they need to mint? And how stable do you
keep those identifiers that they have
already?
>> Uh thank you Matias. I hope you can hear
me. Um I think uh the question would
really be if you're trying to move from
Darwin core archives into the data
package it will be because you're trying
to express more relationships across
your data. And in order to do so, you
would need to uniquely identify the the
entities that are in there. And that
will require defining what would
constitute an ID for the entity that
you're creating. So at the moment, an
occurrence record quite often flattens a
material and the event of the uh
organism existing into one record and
you've got an occurrence ID. It would be
quite likely you'd have to identify how
you would uniquely identify one of your
material records, which would be
something that the the publisher would
have to do. We recognize that uh tools
would need to be uh created um to make
this easier for people um because it's
going to be hard and I would expect tool
developers such as the IP for example to
have to help people manage these things.
I would also expect it that to be the
case that some of the identifiers will
be unique and persist across time while
others might be only uh valid within the
Darwin core data package as it's being
created. So we'll have certain things
like specimen ids which are probably
stable across long periods of time but
there could be others that uh really
only need to exist within that version
of a data set. And I think we'll
probably end up in the situation that
we've got two classes of identifiers.
Some that you can rely on and others
that are really just joining data within
one data set.
>> Matt asks that we introduce ourselves.
>> I'm sorry. I was asked to introduce
myself. I'm Tim Robertson. I'm deputy
director and head of informatics at
GBish.
>> And I was and still am John Vurik.
Thank you very much Edardo Klein from uh
integrated marine observing system in
Australia. Um thank you very much for
the presentation especially the use case
were very illuminating I may say. Um but
um I think that from the provider point
of view this new data schema solves the
problem of the star schema which is the
lack of flexibility basically
but it creates a very complex structure.
It's standardized could be standardized
but it's complex. Now I'm thinking from
the user point of view. The star schema
presents some blockers for the
non-expert user especially the emo the
emo with this long format multiple
possibility of adding variables etc etc.
So you need to know how to work with
that. This schema is extremely complex
for the non-expert user. How do you
think it will be accepted in the
community? Because for the providers
it's perfect. I mean it's perfect. And I
may say if I can accommodate my data
into the Darwin core star schema, I
would prefer to use that.
Thank you.
It's complex.
But it's you have to realize it's only
as complex as you need it to be also. So
you've seen a bunch of diagrams, one
with 20ome tables used, one with six
tables used. It's because they didn't
use all 77 tables that you could use.
They're all there because the model was
built to cover every use case we
encountered. So they all had to be there
to solve something. That doesn't mean
you need it. No. And in fact, you may
not need as many tables for your case as
was seen there. In fact, you may not
need core data package at all because
the star schema isn't really
uh
an obstacle to you.
This week has been illuminating already
starting with the the global nodes
meeting where people were doing
exercises trying to map into this thing
with uh an artificial
uh use case.
From that I got the feeling that a
Darwin core archive serves as a very
good stepping stone to that.
And the thing people need to understand
is what that can do that the archive
can't do and then how much of that is
actually relevant to you and then make
that decision and it's going to be
perfectly fine to stay where you are
with Darwin core archives for a lot of
people but as we've seen in our
community as people start to get
expertise they start to get a little bit
nervous about things that they're not
doing
what they think should be the best way.
So when they get the resources, they
learn and when they get more resources,
they do. And I think that's how it's
going to go that we're going to get
we're as a community, we're going to
evolve into using that when necessary.
>> The the other side of the getting stuff
down,
we're going to share that question.
>> Oh, wow. I feel like I've just been
handed this is this is Tim again. Um
that that's that's a really good uh
question the because some people will
you know want to share simple data and
others will share perhaps more complex
data but then you've got users who will
want the both both kinds of uh
complexity different ranges. Through our
work, we have admittedly been focusing
on how to support the publishing
community. At this point, we have groups
that are frustrated that their Darwin
core archives does not reflect their
research. So, our focus has really been
on that. The challenge I think is going
to be the next stage for us is to start
thinking about what aggregators like
Gibb and others would have to do. and we
we we'll be moving into that kind of
stage. Now the I would expect an
aggregator like GBIF will still need to
produce very simple views of data things
like occurrences uh things like material
cataloges with specimens probably with
relationships across them but that's
already a step forward from what GBIF
can do today. We don't have a material
catalog. We've just got occurrences. We
can't do relationships across material.
So we would I could imagine JBRF would
be able to have simple occurrence views,
a catalog of material and the
relationships, occurrences with the
evidence that supports that. Here are
the the specimens in support of those
occurrences. I could imagine JVI having
a catalog specific to uh the evidence of
organism interactions for example. So
simplified views on top of this richer
model. We don't know what that would be
yet. And at this point what John and I
and the team and everybody has got to is
we're trying to share with you through
the last few years we've been working
with lots of publishing communities.
This is the kind of data that people are
sitting on and want to share and we're
trying to socialize that. We've got it
to this stage. We've got it to a shape
that we think accommodates a lot of use
cases and we want to socialize that with
you with the Tadre community and the
biodiversity community to know what we
should do together to move forward. This
is this is a checkpoint for us. It's a
real big milestone to know you know
people are sitting on this data. We've
heard some case studies where they've
expressed this is what we have and how
it could fit. We've got challenges of
how we might you know operationalize
that but conceptually that's the kind of
structure that people's research is is
accommodating. So we we do need to think
about this I think from the publishing
aspect and the kind of data that they
would they would want or could
potentially share. We then need to think
about what kind of use cases we'd want
to support for accessing this data. And
we haven't we haven't done that exercise
thoroughly yet. But now we have a model.
We could start thinking about those
questions. And I'd invite everybody to
think about those kind of problems. And
then we need to think about, you know,
what should an aggregator like GBIF do?
What should others do? And at what level
of complexity should it be simplified um
as it goes up the chain from the the raw
data up to sort of integration and use.
We need to think through those problems.
But we've now got it to a stage that we
think there is a model to discuss those
things and that's largely why we're here
presenting that to you today. So just to
to recap there, that's to acknowledge we
haven't gone through that process of
thinking about how someone might access
and do questions that integrate all of
this data. But if we were to have that
sort of conceptual model of structure,
we feel that we would be able to ask a
lot of interesting questions here.
over here. There's one over here, too.
>> Go ahead. Sorry, I didn't get the
question.
>> That's okay. Hi. Um, my name's Jane
Anderson. I'm from Local Context, and I
just wanted to ask both uh thank you for
the presentations and for the case
studies. I wanted to ask um the for the
case studies, how you might have been
dealing with indigenous data and just
pulling a thread through from the
keynote this morning. And then this uh
possibility of the data package uh
opening up space for indigenous
interests to be uh included. I just
wonder how you're thinking about that as
well.
>> Very good question. Um the first and
simplest answer is that we haven't gone
through a proper use case and so there
isn't a proper solution to all of the
concerns that come up. However, there
are working groups in Tadwig that are
interested in these things. Um, one of
which is sensitive data that can be
>> I won't cross the lines here with the
same kinds of concerns that you're
talking about. So as
>> this one
>> star for maintenance group which is kind
of responsible for all all of this we're
aware of and trying to make sure that
the solutions that are that come up
there end up in the data package as well
and
it's middle stages in terms of
determining how that works and also
about integrating the care principles
for example into uh usage policy. No, I
I would never claim that usage policy as
it stands in Dracore data package solves
the kinds of issues that will arise
there, but it needs to. And as all
Darmman core things, it's a standard
that's meant to evolve.
An online question from Urit Pulen. I'm
going to paraphrase a little bit. Sorry,
Urit. Um, he wants something clarified.
He asked, "It seems like we suggest that
Darwin core data package introduces a
way to record organism interactions, but
that is also possible in Dorman core
archives. Can you confirm that it is
possible in Darwin core archives through
resource relationship associated
organisms and KT Pearson is backing this
up also with phenological data? I mean
this can be represented with extended
measurement or facts like why switching
to Darwin core arch data packages and
also can you confirm that uh organisms
interactions can be well represented in
Darwin core archives
first what was the second example I got
the whole thing about organism
interactions but there
phenological data
okay I'll deal with organism
interactions the answer is yes the
exercise to uh share organism
interactions via core archives has been
done in the past and there is a
I don't remember it's not called
organism interactions but interactions
uh interest group that has gone through
this as well so yes it is capable of
doing it however
like the obus extended measurements or
facts extension to Darwin core it's a
community understanding about a trick to
do in order to make your data fit in a
DMO archive. It's not particularly
semantically rigorous. It's hard to
recognize a an organism interaction from
a material relationship because it's
just so vague. A resource relationship
is the place to put anything that you
couldn't relate in the model before.
So we knowing that organism interactions
are an important thing we have a
standardsbased place to put them now. So
yes it worked before but you had to
understand how you had to be in the in
group. This will be part of a standard
undocumented.
>> Another online question from Kapia
Molina. He's asking why is Dorin core
data package not using JSON for the EML?
Seems a bit odd to have a data package
JSON and EML XML.
Why not use JSON for Pum?
>> Hi Javier. Um thank you for the
question. Um it was actually to avoid uh
changing everything all in one go
really. Um EML is a is an established
standard. It's been used by our
community in JBIF for you know 15 or or
more years and um we didn't want to
tackle rewriting EML at the same time as
this. Um there are I I would call
attention to the catalog of life data
package um which took the approach I
believe of using uh markdown for the the
metadata and translation tools to go
from markdown to EML. um the the
metadata about the data set is not
really the the focus of uh our research
at the moment. So the the data set
descriptive stuff that's in EML is not
really um what we're we're looking at
with the schemas of the data package.
I hope that answers the question.
We have one more virtual question online
and then I think we'll have time for one
more question in house before the
session is over.
>> Okay,
>> is asking will there be any Darwin core
data package introduction workshops?
already missed it.
It was part of the global nodes
training. Um there won't be any in the
rest of this unless you find me in a
corner and keep me there.
>> Sorry De they there's been a question
identified already.
>> Sorry. H De sorry. Oh harsh. Uh hi John.
Hi Tim. I just this is Shandra. I work
at the National Ecological Observatory
Network at uh in the USA. Um, and I'm
wondering if you could um talk a little
bit how when you were thinking about how
to create the data package, how you
thought about that in terms of how it
would interact with extended specimen
infrastructure and that can either be
from, I guess, the model point of view
or the front-end point of view as well.
>> Aandra, thank you very much. um the the
extended specimen um model and there's
actually many people in the room who've
been heavily involved in that um have
been collaborating uh with us throughout
this process. So in the second session
there will be a presentation recorded
from Sam from Disco in in Europe. Sam
unfortunately couldn't travel um but his
presentation's recorded where the open
DS specification or standard that they
came up with. He demonstrates that he
was able to map it faithfully onto the
Darvin core data package and actually he
he's someone who said it was actually
quite easy and it was easy because all
the target entities existed and he could
just transfer well I've got material it
goes into material got the collection
event it goes onto collection event got
the assertions they go you know and and
for him because the data structure was
already largely aligned it was a fairly
easy data transfer Um, I don't want to
give away the highlights from this
presentation, but I would encourage you
to come and and see that example later.
Thank you.
>> Okay, Deb, we have time for one more
question.
>> Oh, question. It's a comment to add on
to what was said earlier. I think the
point you were pointing out Tim and John
the question that was asked about
whether we should use the data package
as it currently stands or the new one I
I can remember and many of you can I
think we're evolving many of us are
still in collection management software
for example where we're just beginning
to be able to get richer data out using
the extensions that currently exist
right we're getting there I can remember
asking Tim or Marcus at JBIFF and saying
which one of your data sets actually use
the extensions where are they wait I
can't find them right and then it's nice
now in the user interface right we can
we can see them so this this notion of
how do we see the extended data that's
there and I think the new user
interfaces that we're experiencing that
begin to show us biological associations
and relationships we will see we'll
still have rows and columns of data but
we're going to have much richer
visualizations of these data
I think that's where I see that going
based on the history of what we've seen.
So I think it's very exciting. Yes.
Awesome. Thank you very much, Deb. And
that is time for this session. Remember
this is part one. It is time for coffee.
But before you go, I would really like
you to like us all to give a big round
of applause to our presenters. Thank you
so much for presenting your work. I know
except the lots.